1962年9月12日
On the 12th of September 1962,
J·F·肯尼迪总统发表了他著名的 要让人类在十年内登月的演讲
President John F. Kennedy made his famous speech about landing a man on the Moon by the end of the decade.
当时 NASA只有几小时的载人航天飞行经验
At this point in time, NASA had just several hours worth of human spaceflight experience.
许多美国人都以为苏联将成为太空竞赛的最后赢家
Many Americans had accepted that the space race would be won by the Soviet Union,
因为他们已经抢先发射了第一颗人造卫星和第一位宇航员入轨
who had already claimed the records for launching the first satellite and the first human into orbit.
所以为了达成登月的目标
So in order to achieve their goal of reaching the Moon,
NASA需要研发一款大得多的火箭 配上史无前例的大推力发动机
NASA would need to develop much larger rockets with engines more powerful than anything they had made before.
但尺度变大以后 NASA工程师在火箭设计上遇到了前所未有的复杂问题
But scaling up to a much larger rocket design sent NASA engineers into a new world of complex problems.
本期视频我们将了解NASA在F1发动机上遇到的问题
In this video we're going to look at the issues that NASA had with their F1 engine.
我们还将了解他们是如何解决的 以及他们独特的测试方法
We're also going to look at how they fixed these issues and the unusual method they used to test it.
火箭的一级需要五台F1发动机才能将雄伟的土星五号火箭发射升空
In order to lift the enormous Saturn V rocket off the launch pad, it required 5 F1 engines on the 1st stage,
每台发动机可以产生150万磅的推力(约680吨)
each capable of producing 1.5 million pounds of thrust.
想要实现这样大的推力
In order to achieve this amount of thrust,
就需要把超多的煤油和液氧泵入燃烧室
massive amounts of RP-1 fuel and liquid oxygen had to be pumped into the thrust chamber.
在燃烧室 两者混合爆炸 产生推力 将土星五号火箭送上天
Here, the two propellants would combust and lift the Saturn 5 away from the launch pad.
一级火箭在两分钟内烧完的燃料能装满一整个奥运会泳池
The first stage alone would burn through an entire Olympic swimming pool's
worth of fuel in just over 2 minutes.
而制造如此大推力发动机的任务落在了洛克达因手中
The company tasked with making such a powerful engine was Rocketdyne.
他们在几年前为美国空军设计了F1发动机
They had designed the F1 engine several years before for the US Air Force
但美国空军实在没找到这么大推力发动机的用武之地 就把研发工作搁置下来
but after the Air Force couldn't find a use for such a powerful engine, development was stopped.
然后NASA屁颠屁颠来了
Until NASA came along.
在1962年6月 洛克达因准备为F1发动机进行一次长时间测试
In June 1962 rocketdyne were ready to perform a long duration test of the F1 engine.
但当发动机点火 涡轮泵起转时
But as the engine ignited and the turbopumps spooled up,
发动机突然发生爆炸 测试直接彻底失败
the test came to a catastrophic end when the engine exploded.
之后又进行了几次爆炸性的测试 人们才发现问题出在哪
It took several more explosive tests before the engineers finally found what was going wrong
燃烧不稳定
combustion instability.
燃料在燃烧室内燃烧不稳定
This is where the propellants in the thrust chamber burn unevenly
导致了燃烧室内压力的大幅变化
and cause enormous pressure swings inside the chamber.
燃烧室内一部分区域氧气多
As one area of the chamber fills with more oxygen,
产生更多热量 在燃烧室内推动尾焰来回移动
it produces more heat which pushes the flame around in the thrust chamber.
而F1发动机在测试中被炸得稀里哗啦的原因
The reason this was so catastrophic in the F1 engine
是压力的变化会在每秒钟内发生2000次
is because these pressure swings were happening 2000 times a second,
足以使发动机解体
enough to completely rip apart the engine.
当时 阿波罗工程正在紧锣密鼓进行当中
At this point, the Apollo program was well underway
NASA需要为几年后的首次载人飞行准备好能用的发动机
and NASA needed a fully capable engine for the first crewed flights which were just a few years away.
但在这之前从来没造过这样大推力的发动机
But since an engine of this scale had never been made before,
想找到解决办法可没那么容易
the solution to this problem wasn't going to be obvious.
工程师开始研究喷注盘——作用是把燃料和氧化剂送入燃烧室
Engineers started to focus on the injector plate, which feeds the fuel and oxidizer into the thrust chamber.
原本的设计是一个大型喷注盘 上面有很多孔
The original design was a single large plate with multiple injection holes.
虽然这是个很普遍的设计
Although this was a common design,
之前的发动机也没有燃烧不稳定的问题
previous engines never suffered from instability
因为它们的燃烧室很小 燃料也很稳定
since their thrust chambers were much smaller and the propellants were more contained.
为了解决这个关键问题
In order to solve this critical issue,
洛克达因的工程师找来了远古的火箭发动机设计图——V2火箭
Rocketdyne engineers looked back to one of the very first rocket designs, the V2 rocket.
这款火箭是由德国人在二战期间设计研发的
This rocket was developed by the Germans during the second World War
但它却蕴藏着解决F1发动机问题的答案
but it contained the perfect solution to fix the F1 engine.
它没有使用单层平面喷注盘
Instead of a single flat injector plate,
而是使用几个不同的喷管 将燃烧分成不同的流
the V2 featured several different nozzles which separated the combustion into different streams.
工程师认为V2的发动机中更容易控制的分区能够消除燃烧不稳定的可能
The engineers believed that the more controlled sections in the V2 engine
eliminated the possibility of combustion instability.
为了在不彻底重新设计的情况下将它应用在F1发动机上
In order to translate this theory onto the enormous F1 engine without a complete redesign,
工程师们在喷注盘上增加了一些挡板
engineers added a series of baffles to the injector plate
从而把燃烧分成几个不同的区域
to split the combustion up into different zones.
在试验了几种不同的挡板构型后
After experimenting with many variations of baffle designs,
工程师们找到了一种看似可以稳定住燃烧的构型
the engineers came across a layout which seemed to stabilize the combustion.
新的设计投入测试后 发动机的燃烧明显稳定多了
This new design was put to the test and sure enough, the engine executed a flawless burn.
但工程师不相信问题就这样彻底解决了
But the engineers weren't convinced that the problem was fully fixed.
许多人担心发动机在真正上天飞行的时候
Many worried that once the engine was in-flight,
额外的力和震动会重新让发动机进入燃烧不稳定的状态
the extra forces and vibrations could reintroduce instability back into the engine.
所以为了彻底测试一下新的设计
So in order to fully test the new design,
NASA将一个小炸弹放在了喷注盘的中央
NASA placed a small bomb in the center of the injector plate
在发动机点火的时候引爆
and set it off as soon as the engine fired up.
NASA的想法是发动机内部的小爆炸会给发动机带来极大的不稳定因素
The idea was that a small explosion within the engine would create an enormous amount of instability
比发动机正常工作下受到的不稳定因素强得多
far greater than the engine would naturally receive.
当炸弹爆炸时 发动机内部的火焰瞬间变得不稳定起来
When the bomb went off, the flame inside the engine became completely unstable.
但也就在那一瞬间 喷注盘上的挡板开始抑制压力的大幅变化
But almost instantly, the baffles on the injector plate started to dampen the pressure swings
燃烧又变回了稳定状态
and the combustion became stable again.
NASA又执行了多次爆炸测试 确保不稳定燃烧的问题已经解决
NASA performed multiple explosive tests in order to make sure that the combustion instability had gone.
从土星五号首飞到退役
From the first Saturn 5 launch to the last,
65台F1发动机将多名宇航员送入太空 没有发生一次不稳定燃烧的问题
65 F1 engines propelled multiple astronauts into space without any instability problems.
想想在当年那个设计火箭都需要用计算尺的年代
Looking back to a time when rocket engines were designed using slide rules,
前辈们为了克服这些巨大挑战所展现的创新精神 着实让我们敬佩
the ingenuity that was required to overcome these monumental challenges is spectacular.
尽管我们还没有重返月球
And although we have yet to return to the Moon,
我们也应当在实现肯尼迪当年伟大目标的过程中学习他们的智慧与奉献精神
we can appreciate the incredible genius and dedication that went into achieving Kennedy's goal.
Thanks to Brilliant for sponsoring this episode of Primal Space.
There are multiple ways to learn about a topic on the internet,
but the way Brilliant teaches you to think critically about a problem and truly understand it - is unique.
If you liked this video, you probably have an interest in things like space, science, math and engineering - in that case Brilliant has you covered.
Brilliant is a problem solving website with a wide range of interactive courses that break complex topics down into smaller and more understandable chunks.
Brilliant isn't just about memorizing facts and formulas,
it's about developing a deep understanding of how and why things work - so you can apply them to everyday life.
To support the channel and learn more about Brilliant, visit brilliant.org/primalspace.
The first 200 people to sign up will get 20% off the yearly subscription.
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.